现在是冰雹计算
Now it's kind of hailstone computation
所以它朝向序列号和数据
so that it's towards the sequence numbers and the data
结构，而不是打印出来。
structure, instead of just printing it out.
因为Java有两种类型的列表
As Java has two kinds of lists like types
我们可以使用数组和列表。
that we can use-- arrays and lists.
让我们从数组开始。
Let's start by looking at arrays.
数组是其他类型的固定长度序列，
An array is a fixed length sequence of some other type,
例如，t——t可能是int。
t-- t might be int, for example.
下面是我们声明数组变量的方法。
So here's how we might declare an array variable.
这说明a是一个类型为整数数组的变量。
This says that a is a variable whose type is integer array.
然后构造一个分配给它的新数组值。
And then construct a new array value that gets assigned to it.
这里，我们正在构造一个100个整数的数组，
Here, we're constructing an array of 100 ints,
把它赋给那个变量。
and assigning that to that variable.
所以现在重要的是要记住
So now it's important to remember
类型的定义是一组值，
that the definition of a type is it's a set of values,
加上可以对这些值执行的操作。
plus the operations you can do on those values.
好吧，int数组类型包括所有可能的数组
Well, the int array type includes all possible array
所有可能长度的整数的值--100，10，1，
values of integers of all possible lengths-- 100, 10, 1,
55岁，0岁。
55, 0.
但是我们创建的任何特定数组值，比如这个，
But any particular array value that we create, like this one,
一旦它被创造，就永远无法改变它的长度。
can never change its length once it's created.
所以要记住这一点。
So keep that distinction in mind.
现在可以对数组执行的操作
Now the operations you can do on arrays
你可能很熟悉
are probably familiar to you from what
你在Python的列表中见过，所以
you've seen on lists in Python, so you
可以索引到一个数组中，即找到
can index into an array, that is find the value that's
在某个索引处——这将得到第三个元素
at a certain index-- this gets the third element out
在阵列中。
of the array.
这将分配数组的第三个元素。
This assigns the third element of the array.
你可以得到数组的长度
And you can get the length of the array, which
记住，是固定的，但是对于不同的数组可能不同，
remember, is fixed, but might be different for different arrays,
使用点长度。
by using dot length.
所以请再次注意，这些操作都是
So notice again that these operations are all written
以稍微不同的方式。
in slightly different ways.
它们不是简单的方法，也不是简单的函数。
They're not all simply methods, or simply functions.
但基本上还是在运作--
But they are still basically operations--
这是一个需要数组的操作，
this is an operation that takes an array,
并返回一个整数，这是该数组的长度。
and returns an integer, which is the length of that array.
这里有一个使用数组编写冰雹代码的技巧。
So here's a crack at writing the hailstone code using an array.
我们开始，首先，这里
We start, well first of all, here's
冰雹密码的核心我们已经有了。
the core of the hailstone code we already had.
所以它从一些数字开始，n，然后
So it starts with some number, n, and then
只要序列没有达到1，
as long as that sequence hasn't reached 1,
它根据规则更新n。
it updates n according to the rule.
好吧，我们在这里插入，
Well, we're going to insert in here,
保存它遇到的每一个数字，
saving each of the numbers that it encounters,
作为数组的元素。
as an element of the array.
所以这是它存储当前端的地方
So here's where it stores the current end
进入数组的当前索引。
into the current index into the array.
它使用了一个附加变量
And it's using an additional variable, i, in order
穿过那个阵列。
to step through that array.
所以它从index开始，0，然后递增
So it's starting with index, 0, and then incrementing
每次我们在数组中存储一个数字。
each time we store a number into the array.
你会注意到这里，我加上——这个
And you'll notice here, i plus plus-- this
是Java中增加整数变量的运算符。
is an operator in Java that increments an integer variable.
这是我常用的速记法
And that's very common shorthand for i
等于i加1，你可能在其他语言中看到过。
equals i plus 1, which you may have seen in other languages.
最后，我们还要确保
And then at the end, we also have to make sure
我们把最后一个数字，永远是1，
that we put the last number, which will always be 1,
进入那个阵型。
into that array.
现在，有件事很危险
Now, there's something immediately very dangerous
这里——代码中有一个神奇的数字，
here-- there's a magic number in this code,
我们要多谈谈这些数字
and we're going to talk more about these kinds of numbers
后来——这个神秘的常数，
later-- this mysterious constant,
为什么我们在这里选100？
why did we choose 100 here?
事实上，这可能是个错误的选择，
And in fact, this was probably a bad choice,
因为我们不知道冰雹序列有多长
because we don't know how long a hailstone sequence is
很可能得到。
likely to get.
如果我们试着结束
What would happen if we tried an end that
碰巧有一个冰雹序列
happened to have a hailstone sequence that
在它降到1之前反弹了100多次？
bounced around more than 100 times before it got down to 1?
它不适合这个长度为100的数组。
Well, it wouldn't fit into this length 100 array.
事实上，就在这里，只要我们
And in fact, right here, as soon as we
到达一个比我们能适应的更大的i--
reached an i that was greater than what we can fit in here--
长度为100的数组基本上
member that length 100 array will basically
从0到99建立索引。
be indexed from 0 through 99.
所以当我100岁的时候
So as soon as i is 100 here, this statement
会有问题的。
is going to have a problem.
一个问题是，Java是否
And one question is, would Java be
能够静态或动态地捕获这个bug？
able to catch this bug statically, or dynamically?
还是根本抓不到？
Or will it not catch it at all?
答案是它会动态地捕捉它。
And the answer is it will catch it dynamically.
首先，因为它不能静态地知道
First of all, because it can't know it statically
数组a的大小，或者我的大小。
what size array a points to, or just how large i is.
所以Java编译器，看看这段代码，
So the Java compiler, looking at this code,
目前没有足够的信息
doesn't have enough information at this point
弄清楚这是否会是个问题。
to figure out whether this is going to be a problem.
相反，它会遇到这个问题
Instead, it's going to encounter that problem
当它试图索引这个数组时，i等于100。
as soon as it tries to index this array with i equal to 100.
在那一点上，它会抛出一个异常，
And at that point, it will throw an exception,
程序将停止。
and the program will stop.
在Python中，如果您尝试
That's the same thing that would happen in Python if you tried
用更大的数字索引列表
to index a list with a number that was larger
比名单的长度还要长。
than the length of the list.
不幸的是，其他语言尤其不安全
Other languages, unfortunately, particularly less safe
像C和C++这样的语言，甚至不做那种级别的检查。
languages like C and C++, don't even do that level of checking.
他们会让你进入这个数组，
They will just let you go ahead and index into this array,
你会得到垃圾。
and you will actually get garbage.
不幸的是，
And that's responsible for, unfortunately,
大量网络安全漏洞，以及互联网
a large number of network security breaches, and internet
虫子——它们利用这样的虫子，
worms-- they take advantage of bugs like that,
为了进入系统。
in order to break into systems.
所以这可能是一个非常危险的虫子。
So that can be a very dangerous bug.
在Java中，它只会使程序崩溃。
In Java, it just crashes your program.
但在其他语言中，这是非常危险的。
But in other kinds of languages, it can be very dangerous.
所以不是固定长度的数组，
So instead of a fixed length array,
我们改用列表类型吧。
let's try using the list type instead.
可变长度序列列表
Lists of variable length sequences
其他类型的，t。
of some other type, t.
他们更像你
They're much more like what you're
熟悉，概率，来自Python和JavaScript。
familiar with, probability, from Python and JavaScript.
下面我们来声明一个列表变量。
So here's how we declare a list variable.
我们说，这个名为list的变量具有类型list angle
We say, that this variable named list has type list angle
整型括号，闭合尖括号。
bracket integer, close angle bracket.
下面是我们如何构造列表的新实例--
And then here's how we construct a new instance of a list--
我们将讨论一些区别
and we'll talk about some of the distinctions
请稍等。
here in just a moment.
但是在这里，请记住类型是一组值--
But here, remember that a type is a set of values--
所以这是一组列表值。
so it's a set of list values.
下面是可以对列表值执行的操作。
And then here are the operations that you can do on list values.
同样，您可以索引到它们，但是
Again, you can index into them, but instead
在使用方括号语法时，此操作表示为
of using square brackets syntax, this operation is represented
通过方法调用，获取。
by a method call, get.
要赋值，调用方法set。
And to assign, you call the method, set.
要得到列表的长度，可以调用size。
And to get the length of a list, you call size.
这些都是不幸的矛盾
These are unfortunate inconsistencies
在Java中，相对的内部不一致，
in Java, relative internal inconsistencies,
相对于自身。
relative to itself.
Python在这方面做得更好。
Python does this sort of thing much better.
这是Java的缺点之一。
That's one of the drawbacks of Java.
现在，这里还有别的事情。
Now, there's something else going on here.
所以事实上你在申报单上有单子，
So the fact that you have list over here in the declaration,
当你真的
and array list over here when you're actually
构建价值。
constructing the value.
原因是我们会
And the reason for that is something that we'll actually
在以后的阅读中谈论更多，
talk about lot more in later readings,
是因为它分离了类型的概念--
is that it's separating the notion of the type--
所以它是一个列表类型——来自特定的实现
so it's a list type-- from the particular Implementation
它实际上是一个数组。
of that type, which is actually as an array.
所以在Java中，列表称为接口，
So in Java, a list is called an interface,
而且没有任何实际的Java代码。
and doesn't have any actual Java code in it.
相反，它有一组操作声明，
What it has instead is a set of declarations of the operations,
比如get、set和size，一个列表实现
like get and set and size, that a list implementation
必须提供。
must provide.
然而，数组列表实际上是一个类--
Array list, however, is actually a class--
这是一个普通的班级
it's an ordinary class that actually
提供这些操作的实现。
provides the implementations of those operations.
数组列表不是唯一的实现
Array list isn't the only implementation
你可以使用的列表中--这是最常用的一个，
of the list you could use-- it's the most commonly used one,
但链接列表是另一个。
but link list is another.
实际上，现在让我们深入了解一下Java API
Let's dig in now, actually, to the Java API
让你明白我的意思。
so that you can see what I mean by this.
我要做的是googleforjavaapi--
What I'm going to do is Google for Java API--
事实上，我注意到我得到了Java7，
and in fact, I'm noticing here that I'm getting Java 7,
我们在这个类中使用Java8，
and we're using Java 8 in this class,
所以我要稍微改变一下我的谷歌搜索。
so I'm going to change my Google search a little bit.
这个界面向你展示了什么
And what this interface shows you
是所有的类和接口
is all of the classes and interfaces
已经内置到Java中。
that have built into Java.
这里有很多很棒的东西--
There's a lot of great stuff in here--
我特别想深入研究一下这个清单。
I'm particularly going to dig into list.
你会注意到它被称为接口，
You'll notice that it's called an interface,
是一种类型，它是您要放在这里的任何类型的列表。
and is a type that is a list of any type you want to put here.
我们把整数放在这里。
We've been putting integer here.
它代表一个有序的集合。
And it represents an ordered collection.
如果我们向下滚动，就会看到所有的操作，
If we scroll down, we'll see all the operations,
比如get，set和size，你可以在列表中执行。
like get, and like set and size, that you can perform on a list.
但是列表本身不足以使用列表。
But a list is not, by itself, enough to be able to use lists.
我们必须得到这个清单的一个实现--
We have to get an implementation of this list--
我们常用的是数组列表。
a common one that we use is an array list.
实际上在这个列表中有一个可调整大小的数组。
And that's a resizable array actually inside this list.
这个数组列表类只是使用一个数组
This array list class is just using an array
代表你的价值序列。
to represent your sequence of values.
这个类提供所有这些操作
And this class provides all of those operations
这份名单要求它提供。
that list asked it to provide.
所以这是我们的第一次尝试，真的，
So this is our first taste, really,
这门课的核心思想是什么
of what very key idea in this class
将是抽象数据类型——list是抽象数据类型。
will be abstract data types-- list is an abstract data type.
我想让你从中得到的另一件事是
The other thing I wanted you to get from that is it's
知道如何搜索真的很重要
really important to know how to search
用于Java API文档。
for Java API documentation.
我刚才做的有点
And what I just did shows a little bit
关于怎么做。
about how to do that.
现在，这里还有一个重要的调整
Now, another important tweak here
当我们写这些声明的时候
is that when we were writing these declarations, saying
这是一个整数列表，我们使用大写字母i，integer，而不是
that it's a list of integers, we used capital i, integer, rather
比小写int。
than lowercase int.
这是Java的另一个小怪癖。
And this is another little quirk of Java.
这些可参数化的类型，比如list，
These parameterizable types, like list,
很遗憾不能使用基元类型
unfortunately can't use primitive types
作为他们的价值类型。
as their value type.
请记住，原始类型是
Remember that primitive types are
用小写字母拼写——比如int、long和float，
spelled in lowercase-- like int, and long, and float,
再加倍。
and double.
这些基本类型中的每一个都有一个对应的对象
Each of these primitive types has a corresponding object
类型，这基本上是一个包裹在单个值上的对象
type, that's basically an object wrapped around a single value
原始类型的。
of that primitive type.
因此capital I integer是对应的对象类型
And so capital I integer is the corresponding object type
内景。
for int.
在Java中，如果我们要从这个角度
And in Java, if we're going to put something in these angle
可以在集合中使用它的括号，
brackets to be able to use it in a collection,
像一张单子，一套或一张地图，我们
like a list or a set or a map, we
必须使用对象类型，如大写i整数。
have to use the object type, like capital i integer.
幸运的是，Java自动在小写之间转换
Fortunately, Java automatically converts between lower case
整数和大写I整数，所以我们可以简单地编写
ints and capital I integers, so we can just simply write
比如整数I等于5，或者我们可以在代码中写入
something like integer I equals 5, or we can write in the code
我们即将看到，我们可以简单地写下list.add of n，
that we're about to see, we can simply write list.add of n,
即使n是一个int，list包含整数，
even though n is an int, and list contains integers,
Java将自动在它们之间转换。
Java will automatically convert between them.
现在让我们看看用列表编写的hailstone代码。
So let's look at the hailstone code written with lists now.
再说一遍，它的心脏还是一样的--
Again, the heart of it is still the same--
我们有这个起始号码，n，
we've got this starting number, n,
一直循环到1。
and we're looping as long until we get to 1.
更新规则还是一样的，
And the update rule is still the same,
但我们现在已经创建了一个列表变量。
but we've now created a list variable.
我们已将其初始化为新的空数组列表。
We've initialized it to a new empty array list.
每次循环，我们
And every time through the loop, we're
只需调用add将这个新号码添加到列表的末尾。
simply calling add to add this new number to the end of list.
名单会按需要增加，直到我们
And that list will just grow as it needs to, until we've
所有的号码都在里面。
got all the numbers in there.
然后在循环的最后，我们
And then at the end of the loop, we
确保我们添加1作为最后一个元素
make sure that we add 1 as the final element that
冰雹序列。
hailstone sequence.
所以这不仅简单，而且更安全，
So this is not only simpler, but it's also safer from bugs,
因为这个列表是自动的
because this list is automatically
要放大以容纳尽可能多的数字
going to enlarge to fit as many numbers
因为你需要增加。
as you need to add to it.
你也注意到我们不再
And you also notice that we no longer
有一个索引变量
have that i index variable, which
是另一个潜在的虫子来源。
was another potential source of bugs.
如果我们忘记增加i，
If we'd forgotten to increment that i,
我们会有麻烦的。
we would have had a problem.
在我们离开列表和数组之前还有一件事，
One more thing before we leave the lists and arrays,
在Python中你也应该很熟悉，
which also should be familiar to you from Python,
可以使用for循环遍历元素
you can use a for loop to step through the elements
数组或列表的。
of an array or a list.
语法与Python略有不同——这里
The syntax is a little different than Python-- here
就是它的样子。
is what it looks like.
你有一个for循环
You have a for loop in which you have
声明要获取的变量
to declare the variable that is going to take
在列表中的每个值上。
on each value inside the list.
你必须给它一个类型
And you have to give it a type that
与列表兼容。
is compatible with the list.
如果这是一个整数列表--
So if this is a list of integers--
这可以是大写i整数，
this could either be capital i integer,
或者是小写的int，记住
or it could be lowercase int, remember those
是可以互换的——那么基本上我
are interchangeable-- then basically I
对该列表中的每个整数元素运行此循环。
run this loop for each of the integer elements on that list.
你可以遍历数组和列表，
You can iterate through arrays, as well as lists,
如果这个列表是
so the same code would work if this list here were
替换为数组。
replaced by an array instead.
我还想指出math.max--我们提到过
I also want to point out that math.max-- we've mentioned
以前是math.sine，但这是一个方便的函数
math.sine before, but this is a handy function
从Java API。
from the Java API.
记住，你可以简单地用谷歌搜索Java数学API，
And remember that you can simply Google for Java math API,
确保你得到了正确的Java版本，
and make sure you're getting the right version of Java,
你就能找到[？最大值？]
and you will be able to find the documentation for [? max. ?]
就在这里。
And there it is.